Finding Aid for Jenny Lind Club of Detroit records, 1937-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jenny Lind Club of Detroit records 1937-1988
Jenny Lind Club of Detroit.
1.5 linear feet
88274 Bd 2
Swedish American women's organization. Correspondence; minutes of meetings; and yearbooks containing annual reports.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group (Donor No. 7521 ) was donated to the library in 1988; a second accession was received in 1989.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Jenny Lind Club of Detroit, one of many similar clubs named after the nineteenth century Swedish soprano, was founded in April 1937. In an era when many recent immigrants to the United States struggled to maintain close links to the customs and culture of their homelands, the club was established to aid in the perpetuation and encouragement of Swedish cultural and artistic interests in the United States.
The club's membership consists of an elected membership of Detroit area Swedish-American women. Members sponsor and conduct meetings, concerts, and exhibits that are closely linked to the club aims. Charitable concerns have long dominated club activities and fund raisers have benefited a wide variety of organizations and individuals. These include: the Swedish Historical Museum, recipients of the Jenny Lind music scholarship at Wayne State University, the Detroit Swedish Council, Save the Children Foundation, Planned Parenthood, and recipients of the Carl Milles Scholarship at Cranbrook Academy of Art.
The Jenny Lind Club of Detroit records consist of correspondence; minutes of meetings; and yearbooks containing annual reports and clippings files. Ther records are organized into three series: Administrative Records, Yearbooks, and Clippings.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.); Swedish Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Women--Michigan--Detroit--Societies and clubs.; Jenny Lind Club of Detroit.
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records series (1 linear foot) contains a wide variety of materials pertaining to the club and its established mission and aims. The series includes three subseries: Constitutions and legal certification, 1944-1973, Minute Books, 1937-1947, and Chronological Files, 1937-1988. Included in the Chronological Files subseries are minutes for club meetings and board meetings, annual reports of elected club officers, newsletters detailing club activities, press releases to Detroit area newspapers, and correspondence with various parties that reflect the nature of the club's activities and the club's internal working mechanisms.
  - Constitutions and legal certification, 1944-1973 (Box 1)
  - Minute Books, 1937-1947, (Later minutes will be found in Chronological Files.)
    - 1937-1942 (Box 1)
    - 1942-1947 (Box 1)
  - Chronological Files (includes correspondence, press releases and post-1947 minutes).
    - 1937-1988, 52 folders (Box 1)
- Yearbooks
  The Yearbooks series (2 folders) consists of annual reports listing members, the club's constitution (since 1952), activities, and (since 1964) a year-end financial statement. These yearbooks offer a concise listing and reference source for club activities and membership for the years 1938 to 1988.
  - 1938-1964 (Box 2)
  - 1964-1988 (Box 2)
- Clippings
  The Clippings series (6 folders) consists of newspaper clippings and commentary concerning Jenny Lind Club of Detroit activities and news items concerning Sweden and Swedish-Americans. The series is divided into three sub-series: Historian Notes and Newspaper Articles 1937-1972, History 1950-1979, and Lucia Fest 1937-1969.
  - Historian Notes and Newspaper Articles, 1937-1972 (Box 2)
  - History
    - 1950-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 2)
  - Lucia Fest
    - 1937-1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959-1969 (Box 2)